Finding Aid for Emmanuel-Bethel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.) Records 1880-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Emmanuel-Bethel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.) Records 1880-1974
Emmanuel-Bethel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.)
1 oversize folders
(in 11 boxes)
10 linear feet
Royal Oak, Michigan church formed in 1974 through merger of Emmanuel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak) and Bethel Evangelical and Reformed Church (Detroit, Mich.). Reinhold Niebuhr served as pastor of the latter from 1925-1928. Records
9937 Ba 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The church, through Rev. Lawrence M. Wood and board member Betty Mitchell, donated the record group in March 1999. Donor no. 8820
The collection is open for research.
The Emmanuel-Bethel Church of Christ was formed in 1974 as a result of a merger between the Bethel Evangelical and Reformed Church (Detroit, Mich.) and the Emmanuel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.). Since 1974, Emmanuel-Bethel has continued to meet in the Emmanuel church building at 4000 Normandy Road in Royal Oak. Histories of the two separate churches follow.
The Emmanuel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.)
The Emmanuel United Church of Christ had two possible origins in 1873. First, the Congregational Church in Royal Oak recognized the need for services for new immigrants and began to hold bi-monthly services in German. At the same time, the Trinity Evangelical Lutheran Church of Detroit, under the leadership of Rev. George Speckhard, established an orphanage on Main and Third Street in Royal Oak. Speckhard also began holding services for German-speaking people. In 1874, church services at the orphanage began to meet regularly, and the church became known as the German Evangelical Lutheran Church. In 1879, St. Paul's Evangelical Church of Warren accepted the Royal Oak church as a daughter church, and Rev. J. Andres of Warren became the new minister in 1880, serving both the Warren and Royal Oak churches. Some members remained affiliated with the Lutheran Church and formed St. Paul's Lutheran Church in Royal Oak. Rev. O. Keller became the first full-time resident minister for the German Evangelical Lutheran Church in 1908. During his pastorate, the Women's Guild was formed.
Rev. Theodore G. Papsdorf succeeded Keller in 1912, when it became necessary to hold services in English as well as German. At this time, the church had approximately twenty-five families, and was reorganized and incorporated as Emmanuel Evangelical Church. The church subsequently established a Sunday school and a Youth League. In 1913-1914, Emmanuel built a new building and parsonage on the corner of Sixth and Lafayette. German services continued well into the 1920s.
In 1934, the Evangelical Synod of North America merged with the Reformed Church of the United States, and Emmanuel was correspondingly renamed the Emmanuel Evangelical and Reformed Church. By 1935, the church had 250 members. In 1957, the Evangelical and Reformed Church merged with the Congregational Christian Churches, and Emmanuel was again renamed the Emmanuel United Church of Christ.
As membership and services expanded over time, Emmanuel began to look for additional facilities. A major fundraising campaign was launched in 1956, and plans and work for new church buildings began in 1958. In 1964, the first service was held in the new church on 4000 Normandy Road in Royal Oak. Emmanuel's membership and income remained steady into the early 1970s, during which time the church raised money to purchase a pipe organ.
The Bethel Evangelical and Reformed Church (Detroit, Mich.)
In 1912, thirteen people organized an Evangelical Church in Northwest Detroit at the German Protestant Home for Orphans. Later that year, the church was incorporated as the Evangelical Bethel Congregation. The mission board sent Rev. Paul Zwilling to be the first pastor, and services were held at a rented hall on Grand River Avenue. In 1913-1914, the thirty-two member congregation built a new church at the corner of Lothrop and Linwood Avenues in Detroit. The Ladies' Aid Society, later called the Bethel Women's Association or the Women's Guild, was also founded in 1913 to provide spiritual and financial support for the church.
In 1915, Reinhold Niebuhr, then a new graduate from Yale Divinity School, became pastor of the church. During his tenure, membership grew from two hundred-sixty members to over seven hundred, and the church became self-supporting. He inspired the development of the Bethel Brotherhood, the Boy Scouts, a Men's Bible Class, a Women's Bible Class, and a Young People's League. Furthermore, a new church and parsonage were built on West Grand Boulevard in 1921-1922. As pastor, Niebuhr focused on the injustices of the automotive industry and became very active in the labor movement. His experiences in Detroit shaped his thought on sin and grace, love and justice, idealism and realism, and goodness and corruption in human society. In 1928, he accepted a position at the Union Theological Seminary in New York City.
Several short-term pastorates followed Niebuhr, until Rev. Robert C. Stanger became minister in 1933. During his fifteen-year stay, the church organized a board of religious education, began publishing The Bethel Bulletin, and formed the "Double Club" to attract young married couples. In 1934, the name was changed to Bethel Evangelical and Reformed church as a result of the merger between the Evangelical Synod of North America and the Reformed Church of the United States. In the 1930s, Bethel experienced its first problem with declining membership as many members moved to newer parts of the Detroit. The church began to hold Sunday worship and Sunday school at the same time in order to revitalize membership. Stanger also assisted in the establishment of a new mission called Redeemer Church in 1942 and a Home for the Children and Aged on West Outer Drive in 1945. Rev. Robert T. Fauth, later president of Eden Seminary, succeeded Stanger in 1948.
From the 1960s to the merger in 1974, Bethel's membership seriously declined. Many members had moved to the suburbs, and new, younger members did not replace the declining elderly population. The church building on West Grand Boulevard was sold in 1972, and the congregation continued to meet in the Home for the Children and Aged on West Outer Drive. Bethel eventually decided to join with a church of similar ethnic background and denomination. In 1974, Bethel formally merged with the Emmanuel United Church of Christ of Royal Oak, and transferred its remaining one hundred-sixty members to Emmanuel's membership of five hundred.
Pastors of Emmanuel United Church of Christ
1874-1879 Rev. George Speckhard
1880-1883 Rev. J. Andres
1883-1885 Rev. C. Bach
1885-1912 Rev. O. Keller
1912-1916 Rev. Theodore G. Papsdorf
1917-1919 Rev. Armin Haeussler
1919-1932 Rev. Walter F. Hetzel
1933-1941 Rev. W. E. Fisher
1941-1951 Rev. Theophil Goebel
1952-1960 Rev. Jack Yates
1960-1966 Rev. Roy E. Lausman
1967-1974 Rev. Walter H. Harrell
Pastors of Bethel Evangelical and Reformed Church
1912-1915 Rev. Paul Zwilling
1915-1928 Rev. Reinhold Niebuhr
1929 Rev. Adelbert J. Helm
1930-1932 Rev. Charles J. Keppel
1933-1948 Rev. Robert C. Stanger
1948-1956 Rev. Robert T. Fauth
1957-1970 Rev. William Clyde Donald III
1958-1962 (Associate) Rev. C. W. Kohring, Jr.
1968-1970 (Associate) Rev. Rudolph Joop
1970-1973 Rev. Rudolph Joop
The record group is divided into four series: Bethel Evangelical and Reformed Church (Detroit, Mich.), Emmanuel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.), Merger Files, and Emmanuel-Bethel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.). The records of the Bethel Evangelical and Reformed Church are best represented. Some early records are in German.
The records of the Emmanuel-Bethel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.) document the history, membership, activities, and merger negotiations of the Emmanuel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.) and the Bethel Evangelical and Reformed Church (Detroit, Mich.).
The records are significant for documenting the foundation of German immigrant churches in Detroit and for comparing the impact of urban and industrial development on churches in Detroit and its suburbs. The records are also of interest for their coverage of the first and only pastorate of Reinhold Niebuhr, renowned theologian and author.
Subjects:
Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1892-1971.; Emmanuel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.); Bethel Evangelical and Reformed Church (Detroit, Mich.); Emmanuel-Bethel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.); Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Royal Oak (Mich.)--Church history.; Churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Churches--Michigan--Royal Oak.; German Americans--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1892-1971.; Emmanuel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.); Bethel Evangelical and Reformed Church (Detroit, Mich.); Emmanuel-Bethel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.); Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Royal Oak (Mich.)--Church history.; Churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Churches--Michigan--Royal Oak.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Bethel Evangelical and Reformed Church (Detroit, Mich.) 1912-1973
  The Bethel Evangelical and Reformed Church (Detroit, Mich.) series contains 6.25 linear feet of material from this church from 1912 to 1973. Its records have been divided into six subseries: Membership, Administration, Church Organizations, Informational Materials, Photographs, and Publications.
  - Membership
    The Membership subseries is highlighted by two records books chronicling baptisms, confirmations, marriages, and burials. The subseries also contains periodic alphabetic listings of members and a few years of correspondence about the transfer of membership. Membership directories for the 1920s are found in the Administrative subseries.
    - Church Record Books 1913-1973, 2 volumes (Box 1)
    - Alphabetical Lists 1939, 1947, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Transfers 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Administration
    The Administration subseries mostly contains meeting minutes for the church council concerning expenditures, admission of new members, resolutions, reports from committees and pastors, and new programs and services. Monthly financial reports, miscellaneous correspondence, revised bylaws, and annual reports are occasionally bound within these minute books. The subseries also includes separate annual meeting minutes and reports, constitutions and bylaws, and financial reports. Brief annual reports and membership directories were bound together for 1917-1930. Annual meeting minutes are complete for 1937-1961, but scattered for the 1960s and 1970s.
    - Articles of Association, bylaws, and various certificates and legal documents, 2 folders
    - Church Council and Congregation Meeting Minutes
      - 1912-1930, 2 volumes (Box 1)
      - 1930-1936 (Box 2)
      - 1943-1957, 2 volumes (Box 2)
      - 1957-1964, 6 folders (Box 2)
      - 1965-1973, 2 volumes (Box 3)
    - Annual Meeting Minutes
      - 1937-1961, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - 1966, 1968, 1970-1973 (Box 3)
    - Annual Reports and Directories 1917-1930 (Box 3)
    - Constitution 1934, 1939, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1969-1972 (Box 3)
    - Finances 1968-1973 (Box 3)
    - Sale of Church and Parsonage (Box 3)
  - Church Organizations
    The Church Organizations predominantly contains minutes, constitutions and bylaws, and a history of the Women's Guild. There are also three bulletins from the Bethel Brotherhood for 1924.
    - Bethel Brotherhood 1924 (Box 3)
    - Women's Guild
      - Constitution and Bylaws 1942 (Box 3)
      - History of the Founding of Ladies' Aid circa 1915 (Box 3)
      - Minutes 1913-1965
        - 1913-1965, 14 folders (Box 3)
        - 1961-1965, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Informational Materials
    The Informational Materials subseries contains clippings and reflective histories. The illustrated twenty-fifth and thirty-fifth anniversary booklets contain information about the founding of the church, the history of its organizations, the construction of the church buildings, and statements from present and past pastors.
    - Anniversary Materials 1922, 1937, 1947, 1962 (Box 4)
      (includes illustrations)
    - Chart of attendance and budget (Folder 1)
    - Clippings (Box 4)
    - "A History of the Evangelical and Reformed Church in Detroit, Michigan" 1940 (Box 4)
    - Newspaper Clippings about Rev. Reinhold Niebuhr 1971 (Box 4)
  - Photographs
    The Photographs subseries contains numerous unidentified and undated photographs. There are group photographs of youths in confirmation garb with the pastor. There are also photographs of the exterior and interior of the church on West Grand Boulevard and the exterior of three parsonages. Other church activities are also documented, including various social activities, the choir, and boy scouts.
    - Activities (Box 4)
      - Campfire undated, 4 photographs (Box 4)
      - Groups undated, 2 photographs (Box 4)
      - Picnic / Social undated, 19 photographs (Box 4)
      - Play undated, 2 photographs (Box 4)
    - Boy Scouts undated, 12 photographs (Box 4)
    - Buildings
      - Church Exterior Frontal View 1924, undated, 3 photographs (Box 4)
      - Church Exterior Side View 1925, 2 photographs (Box 4)
      - Church Interior undated (Box 4)
      - First Parsonage undated (Box 4)
      - Second Parsonage 1940 (Box 4)
      - Third Parsonage 1952 (Box 4)
    - Choir undated, 3 photographs (Box 4)
    - Confirmations
      - With Rev. Reinhold Niebuhr 1926, 1928 undated, 3 photographs (Box 4)
      - With Rev. Robert T. Stanger undated, 14 photographs (Box 4)
    - Pastors
      - Rev. Reinhold Niebuhr and Family undated, 3 photographs (Box 4)
      - Rev. Adelbert J. Helm undated (Box 4)
      - Rev. Robert Stanger (Box 4)
  - Publications
    The Publications subseries includes programs for the order of worship services from 1922 to 1962. It also contains The Bethel Bulletin for 1938-1961, a monthly church publication that provided news concerning the church, announcements of events, directories of the church council, and a discussion forum for special issues.
    - "The Bethel Bulletin" 1938-1956
      - 1938-1954, 25 volumes (Box 4)
      - 1955-1961, 8 volumes (Box 5)
    - Worship Service Programs and "The Bethel Bulletin" 1918-1921, 1 volumes (Box 5)
    - Worship Service Programs 1922-1933, 6 volumes
      - 1934-1953, 16 volumes (Box 6)
      - 1954-1962, 9 volumes (Box 7)
- Emmanuel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.) 1880-1974
  The Emmanuel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.) series contains approximately 4 linear feet of material from 1880 to 1974. This series is divided into six subseries: Membership, Administration, Church Organizations, Historical and Other Informational Materials, Church Planning and Expansion, and Photographs.
  - Membership
    Membership information includes a registry of members from 1920 to the 1950s, church directories, and records of transfer of memberships.
    - Registry of members 1920-1950s, 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - Directory 1968, undated (Box 7)
    - Membership transfers 1952-1959 (Box 7)
  - Administration
    The Administration subseries contains documentation about the governance and management of the church. Included are annual reports, minutes of the church council and congregation meetings, and various other records.
    - Annual Reports 1953-1975 (scattered) (Box 7)
      (reports also found within the files of the Church Council and Congregation Meeting)
    - Church Council and Congregation Meeting
      - 1880-1919 (Box 8)
      - 1923-1929 (Box 8)
      - 1929-1934 (Box 7)
      - 1935-1945 (Box 7)
      - 1945-1949 (Box 9)
      - 1953-1961 (Box 9)
      - 1962-1973 (Box 10)
    - Committee Lists and Council Rosters 1966-1974 (Box 10)
    - Constitution and Bylaws 1962 (Box 10)
    - Employment of Pastors 1966-1967 (Box 10)
    - Procedures (Box 10)
    - Sale of Parsonage (Box 10)
    - Treasurer's Reports and other financial information, 5 folders (Box 10)
  - Church Organizations
    The Church Organizations subseries includes meeting minutes, bylaws, and constitutions of both the Brotherhood (also known as the Men's Fellowship) and Women's Guild (also known as the Women's Fellowship). Coverage of the Women's Guild is scattered, and coverage of the Brotherhood is fragmentary.
    - Brotherhood
      - Constitution and Bylaws 1965 (Box 11)
      - Meeting Minutes
        - 1924-1932 (Box 8)
        - 1964-1967 (Box 11)
    - Women's Guild
      - Bylaws (Box 11)
      - Meeting Minutes
        - 1909-1917 (Box 11)
        - 1938-1941 (Box 11)
        - 1946-1953, 2 folders (Box 11)
        - 1954-1957, 1970 (Box 11)
  - Historical and Other Informational Materials
    The Historical and Other Informational Materials subseries contains a history of the church on the occasion of its ninetieth anniversary, brochures, and informational mailings.
    - Programs and historical sketch (Box 11)
    - Newsletters and various mailings (Box 11)
  - Church planning and expansion
    - 1953-1965, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Photographs
    The Photographs subseries mostly contains photographs of the church building on 4000 Normandy Road. Two photographs of unidentified youths at their confirmation are also included.
    - Church Building
      - Construction of Church 1963-1964, 13 photographs (Box 11)
      - Exterior View of Church undated (Box 11)
      - Interior View of Church; church members and staff ? undated (Box 11)
    - Confirmations
      - 1938 (Box 11)
      - 1974 (Box 11)
- Merger Files 1972-1973
  The Merger Files series contains records concerning the merger of the Bethel and Emmanuel churches. Included are correspondence, minutes of meetings negotiating the merger, revised bylaws, financial arrangements, and background explanations.
  - Background Information on the Proposed Merger 1973 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence 1972-1973 (Box 7)
  - Pre-Merger Meeting Minutes 1973 (Box 7)
  - Resolutions and Constitution 1973 (Box 7)
- Emmanuel-Bethel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.) 1974
  The Emmanuel-Bethel United Church of Christ (Royal Oak, Mich.) series includes the records of the combined churches after the merger. It contains one item: a history of both churches and their merger in 1974.
  - History for the 100th Anniversary 1874-1974 (Box 7)